{"tossups": [{"question": "An urban legend from this city named <em>P\u00e9r\u00e1k</em>, or \"The Spring Man,\" inspired this city's residents to disobey a Nazi curfew. At an event named for this city, which included the \"Action Programme,\" Jan Palach set himself on fire. The declaration of \u201cSocialism with a human face\u201d was a liberalizing ideology pioneered by Alexander Dub\u010dek [[DOOB-chek]] during a 1968 event in this city, which was ended by a Soviet crackdown. An anti-Soviet \"Spring\" took place in, for the point, what capital of modern Czechia?", "answer": "<b><u>Prague</u></b> (accept <b><u>Praha</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A preacher-turned-union leader in this novel, Jim Casy, is modeled on the ecologist Ed Ricketts, with whom the author of this work co-wrote <em>The Log From the Sea of Cortez</em>. One location in this work is the real-life Weedpatch, a camp run by the Resettlement Administration. The title of this 1939 novel was lifted from a line in Julia Ward Howe's \"The Battle Hymn of the Republic.\u201d For the point, name this Depression-era novel by John Steinbeck which chronicles the Joad family\u2019s exodus from Oklahoma to California.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Grapes of Wrath</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "A ruler of this people passed the Edict of Telipinu, establishing a high court called the <em>Pankus</em> to act as a judicial apparatus for the monarchy. An inscription written in Hieroglyphic Luwian records the first naval battle in history in 1210 BC, during which this empire's Suppiluliuma [[soo-pee-loo-LYOO-mah]] II defeated the Cypriots. This empire\u2019s king Muwatalli II\u2019s ambition to expand into modern Syria led to a clash at Kadesh with the forces of Rameses II. For the point, name this Bronze Age Anatolian empire which established its capital at Hattusa.", "answer": "<b><u>Hittite</u></b>(s) Empire", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A Jewish participant in one of these events, who lectured for the ADL and worked as the \"Lady in Mink,\" was New York City's Department of Consumer Affairs head, Bess Myerson. Robin Morgan protested one of these events at which Peggy Dobbins auctioned off a puppet. Concurrent with one of these events, a Freedom Trash Can filled with \"instruments of female torture\" was created. Jon Katz confirmed the burning of bras in one of these events, and the first winner of one of these events was Margaret Gorman. For the point, name these talent competitions for women.", "answer": "<b><u>Miss America</u></b> pageant (prompt on \"pageant\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "According to biblical accounts, a king of this city named Hiram exported cedarwood to Israel for the construction of the First Temple. A king of this city named Azemilcus unsuccessfully defended it from a siege by Alexander the Great after building a kilometer-long causeway along the water. This coastal city names a purple dye which became synonymous with aristocracy in the ancient world, and it was legendarily the birthplace of Dido, the Queen of Carthage. For the point, name this Phoenician city which, with Sidon, set up many colonies across the Mediterranean.", "answer": "<b><u>Tyre</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In an opera by this composer, the Saracen king Argante abducts Almirena, who sings a plea for freedom in the aria \"Lascia ch\u2019io pianga\" [[LAHSH-ya KEE-oh PYON-gah]]. The premiere of a 1749 work by this composer of <em>Rinaldo</em> caused a three-hour traffic jam on London Bridge. Charles Jennens wrote the libretto for a work by this composer whose performers repeat a line from Revelation 11:15, \"And he shall reign for ever and ever.\" For the point, name this German composer who included the \"Hallelujah\" chorus in his oratorio <em>Messiah</em>.", "answer": "George Frideric <b><u>Handel</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In 1960, this leader gave an impromptu speech which described the struggles of his people as \u201cfilled with tears, fire and blood.\u201d This man was captured while trying to escape his own country by separatists led by Mo\u00efse Tshombe who exerted control of the Katanga Province. This man\u2019s former political ally, Joseph Kasavubu, publicly dismissed him from office shortly before his own deposition by the general Mobutu Sese-Seko. For the point, name this first Prime Minister of the independent Democratic Republic of the Congo who was assassinated in 1961.", "answer": "Patrice <b><u>Lumumba</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A 1389 eponymous battle in what is now this country resulted in the annihilation of the army commanded by Prince Lazar Hrebeljanovic [[reh-bel-YON-oh-vitch]]. This country\u2019s second eponymous battle, in 1448, resulted in the expulsion of the Ottoman Albanian forces by the <em>Srpska [[SERP-SKAH]] despotovina</em>. In 1999, the UN established a mission in this country following a Yugoslav occupation and a NATO bombing campaign. For the point, name this Balkan country, which in 2008 declared its independence from Serbia.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Kosovo</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this conflict, the women of Zapopan formed the \u201cFeminine Brigades of Joan of Arc\u201d to keep male-dominant units supplied. To garner support for this conflict, Ren\u00e9 Capistr\u00e1n Garza went to the US to plead for funds, but US bishops were unwilling to support an armed conflict. Plutarco Calles\u2019s hopes to weaken a religious institution through namesake decrees led to this war, and one side of this war used a flag on which the words \u201cViva Christo Rey\u201d were printed. For the point, name this bloody, anti-clerical war in Mexico in the 1920s.", "answer": "<b><u>Cristero</u></b> War (or <b><u>Cristero</u></b> Rebellion; or <b><u>La Cristiada</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this conflict, the <em>Koreitz</em> cruiser sailed into Admiral Uriu\u2019s fleet rather than accepting an ultimatum of surrender in the Battle of Chemulpo Bay. During this war, one side targeted a European power\u2019s holding of Port Arthur, a Manchurian port between the Bohai Sea and the Yellow Sea. Theodore Roosevelt earned a Nobel Peace Prize for his arbitration during this war, which led to the drafting of the Treaty of Portsmouth. For the point, name this conflict, the first major victory of an Asian power over a European power.", "answer": "<b><u>Russo-Japanese</u></b> War (accept <b><u>Japanese-Russian</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This political leader, who studied under Bronislaw Malinowski at the London School of Economics, was one of the Kapenguria Six imprisoned by British governor Evelyn Baring. During this man\u2019s presidency, the novelist Ngugi Wa Thiongo was arrested on the order of Vice President Daniel Arap Moi for writing <em>I Will Marry When I Want</em>. This president, who first entered the political arena through the Kikuyu Association, later was rearrested for his involvement in the Mau Mau Rebellion. For the point, name this first president of independent Kenya.", "answer": "Jomo <b><u>Kenyatta</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In art, this figure is often shown accompanied by divine milkmaids known as <em>gopi</em>. The <em>rasa lila</em>, or \"dance of divine love,\" takes place in honor of this figure. Indo-Greek diplomat Heliodorus sponsored a pillar dedicated to an aspect of this figure called Vasudeva, who ruled over the Vedic clan of Vrishni. Although he cannot raise his weapon, this figure agrees to be the charioteer of Arjuna during the Kurukshetra War. For the point, name this 8th avatar of Vishnu, a god of compassion and love.", "answer": "<b><u>Krishna</u></b> (prompt on \"Vishnu\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This military event led to clashes between the main army and Khampa rebels fleeing persecution from the government of Liu Wenhui. Shortly before this event, Marxist foreigner Otto Braun and Bo Gu were demoted during the Zunyi Conference. The multiple \u201cEncirclement Campaigns\u201d of Chiang Kai-shek forced this year-long military retreat to Shanxi [[SHAHN-shi]] province. For the point, name this desperate retreat of Chinese Communists led by Mao Zedong to escape the Kuomintang.", "answer": "The <b><u>Long March</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ch\u00e1ngzh\u0113ng</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This political party was split into three \"tendencies\" called the \"prolonged popular war,\" \"proletariat,\" and \"terceristas.\" This political organization allied with the Right in establishing the Junta of National Reconstruction, which was led by Violetta Chamorro. This party ousted Anastasio Somoza and was subsequently led by Daniel Ortega. Opposed by a group of rebels called Contras who were funded by arms sales to Iran, for the point, what is this socialist political party in Nicaragua?", "answer": "<b><u>Sandinista</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Sandinista</u></b> National Liberation Front; or Frente <b><u>Sandinista</u> </b>de Liberacion Nacional; or <b><u>FSLN</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city was sacked and razed by Lucius Mummius in 146 BC, establishing Roman dominance in the region. A league named for this city-state was formed by Phillip II after his victory at the Battle of Chaeronea, allowing Macedonians to assert nominal control over southern Greece. Saint Paul wrote two letters dedicated to the citizens of this city, which names an isthmus connecting Attica to the Peloponnese. For the point, name this Greek city-state which names an ornate style of column.", "answer": "<b><u>Corinth</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "During this dynasty, Bi Sheng invented the world's first movable type technology. The <em>Wujing Zongyao</em>, a military manual written during this dynasty, is the first work to describe chemical formulas to produce gunpowder for military weapons. A feud broke out between Sima Guang and Wang Anshi during this dynasty which broke into \u201cNorthern\u201d and \"Southern\" regions after the Jurchens established the Jin. For the point, name this Chinese dynasty which was eventually replaced by the Yuan after falling to the Mongols.", "answer": "<b><u>Song</u></b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this war, the Siege of Madras and the Battle of Quiberon Bay occurred during the <em>Annus Mirabilis</em>. During this war, Robert Clive recaptured Calcutta and followed that with a victory over Siraj ud-Daulah, the Nawab of Bengal, at Plassey. This war, which was preceded by a shift in alliances called the Diplomatic Revolution, began as a bid by Austria to regain Silesia from Frederick the Great\u2019s Prussia. For the point, name this 18th-century war, which included an American theater known as the French and Indian War.", "answer": "<b><u>Seven Years'</u></b> War (prompt on \u201cFrench and Indian\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In ancient times, the present-day capital of this island was known as both Ziz and Panormus. This island was originally named <em>Thrinacria</em> by the ancient Greeks due to its triangular shape, but its modern name comes from the Iberian tribe which inhabited this island's eastern region as early as 8000 BC. Greek settlers founded the city of Syracuse on this island, of which Palermo is the modern capital. An autonomous region of Italy since 1946, for the point, what is this largest island in the Mediterranean Sea?", "answer": "<b><u>Sicily</u></b> (or <b><u>Sicilia</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A statue commemorating this event was destroyed by The Weathermen during the 1969 Days of Rage. Samuel Fielding gave a ten minute address at this event during which Matthias Degan was killed, leading to the arrest of Oscar Neebe. Two of those jailed after this event had their sentences commuted by Richard James Oglesby. This event involved striking McCormick workers, and Louis Lingg and August Spies [[SPEES]] were apprehended after a bomb attack on police during this event. Albert Parsons spoke during, for the point, what 1886 Chicago labor demonstration?", "answer": "<b><u>Haymarket</u></b> Square massacre (accept \"Affair\" or \"Riot\" in place of \"Massacre\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "With Albert Einstein, this thinker names a 1955 manifesto calling for peaceful resolution of conflicts and the end of nuclear weapons. This thinker divided the title field into \"Ancient,\" \"Catholic,\" and \"Modern\" in his book <em>A History of Western Philosophy</em>. This philosopher promoted his theory of descriptions with examples such as the \"round square\" and the \"present King of France\" in the paper \"On Denoting.\" For the point, name this British philosopher and mathematician, who collaborated with Alfred North Whitehead on the book <em>Principia Mathematica</em>.", "answer": "Bertrand <b><u>Russell</u></b> (accept Third Earl <b><u>Russell</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "On this geographical feature, a Turkic khanate known as the Little Tartary, the longest-lasting successor to the Golden Horde, ruled from 1449 to 1783. Alfred, Lord Tennyson chronicled a failed light cavalry charge during a war on this geographic feature in his narrative poem, \u201cThe Charge of the Light Brigade.\u201d A 1997 treaty enabled the former Soviet fleet in the Black Sea to continue basing its forces on this peninsula. For the point, name this peninsula, which until its 2014 annexation was organized as an Autonomous Republic.", "answer": "<b><u>Crimea</u></b>n Peninsula (accept <b><u>Tauric</u></b> Peninsula)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This leader put down the Praieira Revolt in Pernambuco, which occurred following Liberal and Conservative tension after the Ragamuffin War. This leader was considered the \"Number-one Volunteer\" for his efforts in defending Mato Grosso from Francisco Solano Lopez during the War of the Triple Alliance, in which he allied his country with Uruguay and Argentina. This ruler's daughter, Princess Isabel, passed the \u201cGolden Law\u201d abolishing slavery in a South American nation. For the point, name this final Emperor of Brazil.", "answer": "Dom <b><u>Pedro II</u></b> (prompt on \u201cPedro\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Two answers required. Timothy Snyder wrote a historiography about an area which became a battlefield between these two nations which he named \u201cThe Bloodlands.\" In 1943, one of these nations blamed the other for the Katyn Forest Massacre, a mass killing of Polish officers and other intelligentsia. A non-aggression pact was negotiated by foreign ministers of these two nations, Joachim von Ribbentrop and Vyacheslav Molotov. For the point, name these two powers which fought lengthy battles at Kursk, Leningrad, and Stalingrad.", "answer": "Nazi <b><u>Germany</u></b> and the <b><u>Soviet Union</u></b> (accept <b><u>USSR</u></b>, <b><u>Union of Soviet Socialist</u></b> <b><u>Republics</u></b>, or <b><u>CCCP</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"Russia\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In one of this man\u2019s works, one of the last Assyrian kings watches as his servants are massacred before his eyes. This artist was inspired by an 1825 Ottoman siege to depict Greece as a woman kneeling on the ruins of Missolonghi. In another of this artist\u2019s paintings, Marianne, a symbol of the French Republic, charges forward with a tricolor flag. For the point, name this painter of <em>The Death of Sardanapalus</em> and <em>Liberty Leading the People</em>.", "answer": "Eug\u00e8ne <b><u>Delacroix</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "On this island, James Raymond's troops were defeated by those of Return Jonathan Meigs at Sag Harbor. Tavern keeper William Howard guided the British along the Rockaway Foot Path during a battle named for this island, at which the forces of William Howe defeated those of Israel Putnam and George Washington. The Culper Ring operated at Setauket on this island, which names the largest Revolutionary War battle. For the point, name this island on which the siege of Brooklyn Heights occurred, which caused Washington to flee to nearby Manhattan.", "answer": "<b><u>Long</u></b> Island", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This document made the news in 2018 when Mark Royden attempted to steal it as he believed it was a fake. The modern system of numbering the \"clauses\" contained in this document was introduced in the 18th century by the author of <em>Commentaries on the Laws of</em> <em>England</em>, William Blackstone. This document was drafted by Archbishop Stephen Langton, and Henry III attempted to create a \u201cnew\u201d one in 1225 to legitimize his rule. For the point, name this royal document signed in Runnymede by King John to placate rebellious Barons.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Magna Carta</u></b> Libertatum</em> (accept <b><u>Great Charter</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After living with a member of this family, Quispe Sisa married Francisco de Ampuero. Members of this family named Gonzalo and Hernando worked with Pedro de Valdivia to defeat Diego de Almagro at the battle of Las Salinas. Another member of this family sailed with Alonso de Ojeda and tried to arrest Vasco de Balboa. That man in this family lost the Battle of Punto Quemada but led the Famous 13 and won at Cajamarca in his conquest of Peru. For the point, name this family of <em>conquistadors</em>, including Francisco.", "answer": "<b><u>Pizarro</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A set of underground nuclear tests with this name were conducted in 1971 in an attempt to excavate for the Pechora-Kama Canal as part of the \"peaceful nuclear explosions program\" of the Soviet Union. Near the Tunguska River in 1908, the airburst from a large meteoroid destroyed approximately 830 square miles of a biome with this name. The 2014 Funny River Fire burned nearly 200,000 acres of Alaskan black spruce, a staple of this biome in North America. For the point, name this biome, also known as snow forest or boreal forest.", "answer": "<b><u>Taiga</u></b> (accept <b><u>Snow Forest</u></b> or <b><u>Boreal Forest</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The National Quartet Dialogue, which emerged from this uprising, led to the awarding of the 2015 Nobel Peace Prize, four years after the self-immolation of Mohamed Bouazizi. Political dissidents during this uprising organized mass demonstrations in Tahrir Square. Muammar Gaddafi initially responded to his country\u2019s participation in this uprising by reducing food prices and restructuring the military, though he eventually ordered his army to open fire on protesters in Benghazi. For the point, name this 2010-2012 Middle Eastern uprising which provoked the Libyan and Syrian civil wars.", "answer": "Arab Spring (accept Jasmine Revolution until \u201cTahrir\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country created the \"Stop-at-Two\" program to sterilize women, and Constance Goh founded this country's family planning association. Many low-income women in this country were stereotyped in the Great Marriage Debate. Changi Prison in this country housed British prisoners of war in World War Two. According to legend, the last tiger in this country was killed next to the Raffles Hotel. Once governed by Lee Kwan Yew, for the point, what is this Asian city-state next to Malaysia?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Singapore</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}